hey guys welcome back to another final
cut pro tutorial and today
we're learning all about how to color
correct and color grade our footage
so we're going to start with beginner
and move all the way up to intermediate
advanced i'm no colorist but i'm going
to tell you the workflow that i follow
so we're going to first start with our
correction and fixing the colors
and exposure in our clips then moving on
to
unique situations like we're underwater
or when the drone is panning
and the exposures or colors are changing
and finally we're going to finish
off with color grading and giving our
footage a
look and a final result something that
we are happy with
so let's get into it all right here is
our editor
it's completely empty except for some
footage on the side first thing we want
to do when it comes to color grading
is open up our preferences
and select here like i already have
selected color wheels we don't want to
use color board as it doesn't give us
as much freedom as color wheels so
select that
all right next we're gonna drag a clip
into the timeline for example this
clip here of iceland now we wanna start
correcting
this footage so we're gonna go to view
look at video scopes
[Music]
and here are the two scopes that i
always select i have the vector scope
and i have rgb overlay and the way you
can change that
is by selecting them on the side here
also here
by clicking view you get to select two
one three or something like this
but i always like just these two all
right let's get a better look
at this and a bigger screen what you
want to do is
bring these colors you can see here you
want to try and bring them together
and we do that over here in the color
wheels so let me briefly explain on the
right side of the color wheel we have
exposure
and that's on the master wheel that's
the whole image on the left side we have
saturation up and down
and down at the bottom we have white
balance on the right side we warm up the
photo on the left we cool it down on the
video sorry
and the bottom is the magenta and greens
on the opposite sides of the color wheel
so let's go back to the master and if
you notice on the other sides of the
wheel we have orange
and the opposite is teal so we have
yellow then we have blue
and on the other side we have magenta
and green and notice how that affects
the rgb overlay on the left side here
the more saturated the color the higher
it will be in the chart
and the other wheels on the charts such
as mid-tones shadows and highlights are
for more control
within our adjustments all right let's
get started and color correct this
footage
starting with the white balance so by
sliding
it to the right you can see the colors
come together so that pulls a bit of the
blues out
so as you can see the reds are still
lower than the other ones so we can try
and add reds in the highlights to raise
them up
there we go now you can see they're
completely aligned
so let's toggle that on and off to see
the difference as you can see the clip
was a little bit blue before
and now it looks a little bit better
colored
with the white here is the luminosity or
the luma and you want to bring
this one this line here all the way up
to close to 100 and the bottom
down to zero usually you want to start
with that so we'll bring down shadows
the minute you touch the line that means
you've lost information in the shadows
and that's called crushing the blacks
and then we're going to raise the
highlights
all the way up close to 100 sometimes
you can go over
if you want that look it's fine for
example there's no information in the
sky but if you like that look that's
fine
so we'll bring them just to 100.
and as you can see there's still a
little bit of darkness here so i'm going
to raise the mid-tones
that brings the detail back into the
shot
sometimes when you raise the mid-tone
too high you can bring down the shadows
again
all right that shot looks better let's
toggle it on and off
so that right there is corrected footage
let's move on to another clip
as you can see in this shot it's a bit
pink in these mountains
so we want to correct this by pulling
the magenta out of this tint as you can
see right away it's looking better
by adding green second of all we can
bring down the shadows right down to the
bottom
we can raise the highlights a bit but as
you can see we've got a bit of a green
peeking over here in our highlights so
we can pull highlights
away from green because that is the
opposite outside on the color wheel
let's pull highlights away from green
you see what's happening
well that brought more pink into the
photo we can desaturate the highlights
to get rid of some of that pink all
right let's bring mid-tones down
get them down we're losing detail in
this waterfall at the top here
so we've got to bring those highlights
down a bit there still
a little too much pink overall in the
photo so i'm going to pull the mid tones
away from pink
there we go so now we've fixed that
problem of the greens and the highlights
and we've balanced the color a little
bit better let's look before and after
so as you can see it was pink here the
image is a bit flat
looks much better now let's try another
clip and let's say
we're using this interview footage
whenever you're using
interview footage you always want to
start by making a compound clip
interview one because when you have this
interview let's say you're cutting it up
and you're fixing all of the errors in
the interview
if you're then you pull that out so
let's say i want to fix this clip right
here
and i want it to affect all of my pieces
i just double click
and now i fix this bring the shadows
down
raise the masters
that way when i go back into the clip
that's affected all of them together
alright next we'll look at some log
footage here we have
two clips one is a little bit blue
and one is a little bit orange
so as you can see here we've got the
blue and the highlights
and we need to correct that so right
away we can pull
some orange into the clip and all of a
sudden you see
our colors are lining up we got to put
more reds into the highlights
and as you can see they're lining up and
we will
bring the shadows down bring all the mid
tones up to get more
light in the shot highlights up
we've got a bit of clipping here so
maybe we won't go too high
shadows down okay let's look at a really
orange shot
so the white balance was off on the
camera here made a mistake if you want
to correct for that we have way too much
red
so let's bring blue back into the shot
as you can see
the red is coming down and we're in the
mid tone area
let's pull away from red
[Music]
or we can do the whole thing all the way
from red add some more blue to the shot
and now let's contrast
let's bring the mid tones up
still a little bit too much red
let's pull away from magenta add some
green
there we go let's that looks a bit
corrected
[Music]
much better so as you can see there's
some clipping here but that's no problem
that's just the light in the windows
that's no worries so that clip looks
much better
let's look at another shot here when we
have the cup the white balance is
way off if we have a scenario like this
and we want to
match these grades we just copy ctrl c
and over here shift ctrl v
and that will add the attributes so
there we go color wheel
add and all of a sudden we have matching
clips
so we've shared our color color
correction onto the other clip
excuse the background noise that's my
mac
humming to try and keep up with the
screen recording here
next let's look at two unique scenarios
so one is underwater footage
look at the difference in the color here
so every time we shoot
underwater we lose the reds so we have
to bring back the reds in the shot
because it's
definitely blue dominant so right away
let's add some magenta
let's add red into the mid tones with
this you kind of gotta play around with
it to try and get the best looking image
so bring we can bring the shadows down
to the bottom
[Music]
you can raise it up a little bit
highlights can go up a bit we're going
to lose some but that's okay
let's bring more red into the shot raise
that right up
bring that down we don't want to lose
too much blue because of course we are
under water after all so we don't want
this color to be red or green we want
someone to be blue however look at the
detail we brought back into the
subjects look at how much contrast and
color
back natural color back we can make this
more saturated we just boost these
colors
and that way we can still hold on to the
blue so next we have a drone shot what
happens when
drone pan is down is it's too dark right
as we hit here
we want to put in a keyframe right here
we want to go to the middle of our clip
and that's what we want to
fade on some more
exposure here and
here and now watch our clip adjust as it
pans down
it's panning down and it adjusts
all right so these clips that you see
here i've actually got from
storyblocks which is the sponsor of
today's video
storyblocks has 1 million royalty-free
assets
i've been using this service for 2 years
now and it's awesome it's an affordable
subscription
with unlimited downloads it's a big time
saver for example sometimes i'm editing
winter footage in the wrong season i'm
in a hot place
storyblocks comes to the rescue and i
can get some snow footage or whatever i
need to fill in that spot
if i'm in a different country and i am
missing some b-roll of that country
storyblocks has footage from all over
the world which is amazing
you can just get back to editing and
finishing more projects
if you're interested in using star
blocks check the link in my description
for more all right so here we are to the
last portion of the video and that
is the grading portion of the video
giving it its final look
so what we do here i have some clips
from iceland i'm going to drag over an
adjustment layer so i can apply the look
to all of the clips
now this only works after we've color
corrected all the clips
you can't just slap on a lut or a grade
and expect it to
fix all of your clips we have the color
correct then we can put on our look
and it can apply to all the clips if you
don't have an adjustment layer in your
final cut already link is in the
description or you can download a free
one
so here we can adjust the colors of our
clips let's say we want to bring
our shadows into this range here and
maybe our mid tones we want to make more
orange
let's say we want to make the master
more colorful so here's where we can get
a bit more technical we bring in our
color curves
we can if you want you can bring more
contrast into the image by
doing a slight s curve if you want more
of a hazy moody
summertime vibe you can add some fade
to it that could that might be a look
that you want for some films not
typically
travel too much bring that back
now we're going to go to hue saturation
curves this is where we can get really
technical with the various colors
so let's say we're adding just this
single clip and we have a hue saturation
curve
we will select the hue by clicking on
that
let's say we want the yellow and now we
can adjust
the color of the grass so look more
green more orange we're going to do it
to the whole
adjustment layer so let's go greens
let's bring them more
no we want to adjust like this
so the yellowish greens we want to bring
them into the more of a more orange
range
and then whenever you're looking at a
color grade you want to look at the
opposite
side let's look at this color here click
on it
there it is and you can see i can make
it more teal or make it more purple
depending on how you like so that's
where you have the freedom
to work with the colors in the hue
saturation and
luma curves let's see we want to adjust
the brightness of the blues we click on
the eyedropper
we click over here and we can bring up
the brightness of the blues
all right we have talked a lot about
landscapes now look
now let's look at some portraits
so we have three portraits here and
that's where our
vector scope comes into play this line
here regardless of ethnicity
is the skin tone line and you always
want to line up your
luminosity and your color along that
line so this one's a bit too orange
needs to be a bit
more along there so that's properly
corrected now let's say we want to add
a more of a grade to this for example
let's say like a teal
look and orange in the highlights
what i don't like about that is his
beard has kind of gone aqua
let's have a look the way to fix that is
we go to our
hue saturation sliders we put option
click this is our luma line so this is
the shadows
this is the highlights so if we pull
that down
you can see that actually pulls the
color
out of his beard see that
because there's nothing worse than teal
shadows
all over a video just kidding kind of
okay next one we're going to do color
masking so click over here color mask
and want to
select your skin tone with the
eyedropper tool then view the mask and
we're going to
slide these hsl bars all the way
until her skin tone is completely white
we're going to mask out her entire
skin so once you've successfully done
that then you're going to click
on view mask again to see the image
select outside and we want to change the
color of the outside when we adjust the
master wheel it's a bit aggressive so
let's reset that
do the mid tones and as you can see
we're changing the
background and the darker parts of the
photo so this is completely subjective
when you're creating looks it's
completely up to you lastly i'm going to
pull
the color out of the shadows like i did
last time
and there we go i've completed it let's
take a look at the before and after
so once you understand how the color
wheels work a little bit you can play
around with the colors and pick a look
that you like
however if you want to try out the
colors that i use in all my travel
videos
then just click the link in the
description and you'll see my luts there
for sale
and you're looking at four of the before
and afters of four of my luts
in my latest pack they're super easy to
add to your footage you just type in lut
add that custom lot on top of your
footage go to the drop down menu
markers and luts and pick one of them
and there boom done if i provided you
with some value i'd appreciate it if you
checked out that link
all right that wraps up for today's
video i hope you learned something in
this color green tutorial make sure you
follow me over on instagram
give this video a like and subscribe if
you aren't already and we'll catch you
in the next one
[Music]
so this is um so with underwater
and and
do i